Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is פ"ז, pei zayin,
בבא בתרא Bava Batra eighty-seven. We are in the middle of a
statement of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel that we pick up on
the, I should say, the second to last line of פ"ו עמוד
ב'. pei vav amud bet. תא שמע, ta shma, we're dealing with
a statement of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel who said that if
somebody says I'm selling you a כור kor
for thirty dollars, then that's one unit and the sale is not
final until the entire כור kor is measured out. However, if he
said, I'm selling you a כור kor for thirty dollars, one dollar
per סאה, se'ah, there are thirty סאה se'ah in a כור, kor,
then each סאה se'ah is a separate, implicitly a separate sale and
it's final when each סאה se'ah is measured out. Okay, and we
challenged that yesterday, the end of the day yesterday with something that
indicated that we would always look at it as each little bit
is being sold and the גמרא Gemara says no, that was when
it was framed in that way,
a סאה se'ah per dollar, not as the whole כור. kor. But
when it's framed as the whole כור, kor, it's only the whole
unit. Now we're going to look at a ברייתא braita that seems
to indicate the other way, that we always look at things as
one whole unit and not as the sub-units. So let's take a
look. תא שמע, ta shma, השוכר את הפועל לעשות עמו לגורן היום
בדינר, ha-socher et ha-poel laasot imo legoren hayom b'dinar, ולגורן יפה סלע.
u'legoren yafeh sela.
So somebody wants to hire workers. Now at the time of harvest
there's a very high demand for workers, so workers can demand a
סלע sela per day. A סלע sela is four דינר. dinar. But
now it is months before and you go over to a worker
and you say I will hire you for thirty days of work
at harvest time and I am going to give you not thirty
סלע sela but thirty דינר, dinar, a quarter of what you would
normally make. And you agree to it because you need the money
now. So the הלכה halacha is, so that's what it says, השוכר
את הפועל לעשות עמו לגורן היום בדינר, ha-socher et ha-poel laasot imo
legoren hayom b'dinar,
you are now contracting with him to pay him a דינר dinar
for every day during the harvest season, ולגורן יפה סלע u'legoren yafeh
sela but when it actually is the harvest time that work is
worth a סלע, sela, four times as much. So it says, אסור
ליהנות ממנו, assur l'hanot mimenu, you cannot derive benefit from him meaning
that deal is not accepted because essentially what he is doing is
he is accepting a much lower price for his labor
because you are giving him the money in advance. You are fronting
him the money. So that feels a type of ריבית. ribbit. You
are giving him money, because you're giving him money earlier and he
pays back, as it were, later, he gives you his labor later,
and when he gives it back it's worth much more. So that
is seen as a type of ריבית. ribbit. Even though it's not
a loan, we do know that this type of a thing is
there that רבנן, rabanan, they would look at other transactions also that
could be quasi ריבית ribbit or אבק ריבית avak ribbit at a
rabbinic level. So that's forbidden. אבל אם שכרו מהיום בדינר ליום, aval
im s'charo mehayom b'dinar l'yom, ולגורן יפה סלע מותר. u'legoren yafeh sela
mutar. However,
if you hired him today, it was a month before the what
do you call it, it was a month before the harvest season
and you hired him for two months and I'm starting today and
I'm going to pay you a דינר dinar a day, okay, and
we're contracting for two months, and here are sixty דינר. dinar. So
the first month is pre-harvest, the next month is harvest. In that
case, it's okay. It's not considered that you gave him money up
front for something that would only be paid later when it was
worth more. Why? Because right now you've contracted him for the whole
sixty days and the work starts right away, so it's not something
given now for something paid back later. No, it's something given now
for something that is beginning to be given right back right now
as well. The sixty days starts being paid back as it were,
or the contract starts immediately. So that's acceptable. Now that only makes
sense if we look at the sixty days you hired him for
as a unit and then you can say the whole unit I
bought that unit as it were to be for sixty דינר. dinar.
But if you look at each day separately, then you are still
buying units later on for less than their price right now. Okay,
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ואי סלקא דעתך ve-ee salka daitach כור בשלושים סאה בסלע אני מוכר
לך kor bishloshim se'ah besela ani mocher lach ראשון ראשון קנה, rishon
rishon kana, now if you think that when somebody mentions both the
total and the individual, I will sell you a כור kor for
thirty for thirty, you know, a סאה se'ah per... let's read that
again. כור בשלושים סאה בסלע, kor bishloshim se'ah besela, I will sell
you a כור kor for thirty סלע sela which is a סאה
se'ah for a סלע... sela... excuse me, let me read that again.
כור בשלושים סאה בסלע, kor bishloshim se'ah besela, I will sell you
a כור kor for thirty סלע, sela, which is a סאה
se'ah for a סלע. sela. So I'll just say dollar, I'll sell
you a כור kor for thirty dollars, each סאה seah for a
dollar. You say both the total amount and the sub-unit. If we
think we should come, if we think that at that case we
should מיפסק פסק mipsak pasik that at that it's considered to be
the each sub-unit is a sale even though you also mentioned the
bigger collective. So הכא נמי כמה כמה מפסקי פסקי ואסור להנות מהם
בסוף להנות מהם. hacha nami kama kama mipaskei paski ve-asur le-hanot mehem
basof le-hanot mehem. So here too if you say I'm hiring you
for sixty days, a dollar per day, a דינר dinar per day,
so that's both the total amount and the sub-amount and therefore it
should be focused as each one being a separate sale, and as
such you're paying him money now for labor he's going to pay
you back later at when it's worth a lot more. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so let's read it then. הכא נמי כמה כמה
מיפסק פסק ואסור להנות ממנו. hacha nami kama kama mipsak pasik ve-asur
le-hanot mimenu. So if that's true it should be each one should
be separate and you should be forbidden. So if that's true מדינר
ליומא ולגורן יפה סלע מותר, mi-dinar le-yoma u-le-goren yafeh sela mutar, how
could it say that when you say you start it right now
it's permissible? אמאי, amai, why is that true? והא אגר נטר ליה
הוא, ve-ha agar natar lei hu, it is אגר, agar, שכר, sechar,
for watch it for me. You are giving him money in order
for something that has to be
now for allowing you to pay back later, right? That is what
a loan with ריבית ribbit is. You give me a hundred dollars
now and I will give you a hundred and ten dollars because
you're letting me pay it back later. So in this case if
we look at each day as a separate unit, I am giving
him sixty דינר dinar now, okay, but thirty of those דינר dinar
I am giving him for the work he's going to do at
the harvest, I'm giving it to him now, he's going to pay
it back to me later when it's worth four times as much.
If you consider it all a unit, I paid him sixty and
right now he's giving me sixty, it takes sixty days to pay
it, but it's all one big unit. But if each one is
a separate unit, I'm giving him the money for the harvest now,
which he's going to be paying me back with work later when
it's worth more. So how is that acceptable? So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רבא ותסברה, amar Rava ve-tisbera, Rava says one minute, does
this make sense that this real any of this should really be
a problem? זלזולי בשכירות מי אסר? zilzulei bi-sechirut mi asar?
Since when is it forbidden for a person
to sell themselves out, rent themselves out at a low price? There's
no sense of a fixed price.
So what does this mean? The way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it
is the following: This isn't a loan, right? So because it's not
a loan it shouldn't be ריבית ribbit all together. Now,
however, חז"ל Chazal did make an אבק ריבית avak ribbit type of
a scenario by a sale.
So if I
basically give me ten dollars today and I give you in a
month from now twelve dollars of produce, even though that's a sale,
it's sort of like a loan with ריבית. ribbit. You give me
something now, I give it back to you later and it's even
more that I'm giving back to you. That's okay, but there the
רשב"ם Rashbam says we know there are הלכות halachot about what the
right value is for items because there are הלכות halachot of אונאה
ona'ah of overcharging. So therefore you actually could objectively say you are
giving him something that is worth more than what he paid you
because there is a market rate, a going rate, and הלכה halacha
pays attention to that. When it comes
to hiring a laborer, so there is no הלכות halachot that recognize
oh you're overcharging for your labor, you're undercharging for your labor, they
don't pay attention or claim to look at anything like a market
rate.
And therefore everybody is free to rent themselves out
at whatever they want or to hire a worker at whatever he
wants, so there's no minimum wage. So in that case Rava says
זלזולי בשכירות מי אסר? zilzulei bi-sechirut mi asar?
So
even if you give me ten dollars today and I give you
back labor that at the time I'm giving it you back mostly
is worth twenty dollars because that's the standard, but הלכה halacha doesn't
recognize that as having a fixed twenty dollar value even if it's
the standard right now and I can give it away for ten
dollars if I want to. Okay, so therefore there's no real ריבית
ribbit problem of giving something that's objectively worth more giving it back.
All right, well if it's not a problem then why is anything
אסור? asur?
So if that's true says the גמרא Gemara מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha u-mai shna seifa? So what is the
problem in the first case? רישא דלא קעביד בהדיה reisha dela ka'avid
be-hedeih
in the first case where he says start working for me in
a month at the harvest season, מהשתא מיחזי כאגר נטר ליה. me-hashta
michzei ke-agar natar lei.
It looks like it's not that your real אגר נטר agar natar
is give it to me today and I'll pay you back more,
or you know, even if it's a sale. item I’ll give you
in a sale will be something of higher value later. So רבא
Rava is saying objectively speaking that does not exist by שכירות. sechirus.
There’s no objective sense of how much this labor is worth. And
therefore it is really not a formal problem of
אגר נטר. agar natar. But because the payback doesn't start immediately, it
takes on more of that form. The money is now, big break
in time, payback is later, and at a time when normal people
would charge more. That looks much more like a type of a
loan בריבית. beribis. However, סיפא דקעביד בהדיא, seifa de-ka’avid behedeya,
in the second case when the work starts immediately, מהשתא לא מיחזי
כאגר נטר ליה, mehashtah lo mechzi ke-agar natar lei, so then it
doesn't appear. The key difference here is the word appear. Technically speaking
you are right, in a formal sense, okay, each day is different,
and you still paid him sixty dollars, and thirty of those days
it's going to be worth a heck of a lot more than
thirty dollars, okay, and each day is different. But that’s objectively speaking.
But objectively speaking there’s also no אגר נטר, agar natar, because there’s
no fixed value of labor. And since there’s no fixed value of
labor, he did not give you back something objectively worth more. There
might be the standard people are renting themselves out but we don't
objectively say that labor was worth more than the money he got.
The only problem is appearances. And for appearances’ sake, when there’s a
break it looks like a type of a ריבית, ribbis, and when
it’s immediate, it starts immediately, even though each day is seen as
distinct halachically, but when it starts immediately it is not the appearance
of something that looks like ריבית. ribbis. Okay, let’s last section now
of the משנה. mishnah. ואם היה מחובר לקרקע ותלש כל שהוא קנה.
ve-im hayah mechubar la-karka ve-talash kol she-hu kanah.
If the flax was connected to the ground, as soon as he
rips up a little bit of flax from the ground, he acquires
all the flax he’s trying to buy. So that’s from the משנה
mishnah for those who forgot. So the גמרא gemara says, ואם היה
משום דתלש כל שהוא קנה? ve-im hayah mishum de-talash kol she-hu kanah?
I don't get it. Because he picked up a little bit of
this, he’s קונה koneh the other stuff? The other stuff is still
attached to the ground. What type of a קנין kinyan did he
do on all the other flax? So אמר רב ששת, amar Rav
Sheshet, הכא במאי עסקינן דאמר ליה לך יפה לך קרקע כל שהוא
וקני כל מה שעליה. hacha be-mai askinan de-amar lei leich yafei lach
karka kol she-hu u-knei kol mah she-aleha.
The owner says to him: go, make the land a little bit
better, improve the land a little bit. Okay, so now we’re conceptualizing
the pulling up of the flax not as like doing a הגבהה
hagbahah on the flax, but what we’re conceptualizing it is doing an
improvement on the קרקע, karka, you’re cleaning it up, you’re making it
more prepared for threshing, or if it’s the time for harvesting then
plucking it is making it better, it’s bringing the land to the
next stage, and that’s a קנין חזקה. kinyan chazakah. חזקה chazakah on
land is made when you do something to improve the land. Okay,
and therefore go and improve the land and take possession of all
of the flax that is growing from it. So really what we’re
dealing with here is a קנין חזקה kinyan chazakah on the land.
Now, how does that work? So רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot have
two slightly different interpretations. רשב"ם Rashbam says
the flax itself has a status of קרקע, karka, it’s connected to
the ground. So the same way you could be קונה קרקע koneh
karka by a חזקה, chazakah, you could be קונה koneh the flax
by a חזקה, chazakah, and you’re doing now a קנין kinyan on
the ground, so it’s a קנין kinyan that works on קרקע, karka,
so it’s a קנין kinyan that works on the flax which is
considered קרקע. karka. The problem with that is that the flax is
not the same קרקע karka that you’re improving. You’re improving the actual
dirt, you’re not improving the flax, and each flax is like a
separate unit. So how did that חזקה chazakah you did on the
dirt work for the flax? So what תוספות Tosafot says is that
you really are קונה koneh the קרקע karka underneath the flax, not
a full קנין, kinyan, but you are קונה koneh it enough, like
you sort of rent it, and it’s enough of a קנין kinyan
that now it’s considered your רשות reshus for the purpose of taking
possession now of the flax that’s growing from it. So your רשות
reshus is קונה, koneh, that’s a קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer, and then
your ownership of that land stops. Okay, very interesting. Let’s take a
look now at the next משנה. mishnah.
המוכר יין ושמן לחבירו. hamocher yayin ve-shemen le-chavero. So before we were
dealing with when the קנין kinyan is final, now we’re going to
deal with questions about measures, just weights and measures and making sure
you’re giving somebody everything that they are purchasing. Okay? So המוכר יין
ושמן לחבירו, hamocher yayin ve-shemen le-chavero, somebody who is selling wine and
oil to his friend and these are liquids which are viscous and
they adhere to the sides of the vessel. והוקרו או שהוזלו. ve-hukru
o she-huzlu. Oh, I’m sorry, I’m jumping ahead. We’re still in when
the sale is final. We’re going to get to the just measures
in a minute. Okay? So you were going ahead and pouring out
the wine and oil and now the price has changed and one
side wants to back out. The price doesn’t have to change to
want to back out but that would be a common reason why
one side would. wants to back out. So we're still at the
question of when the sale becomes final. So the
משנה Mishna says אם עד שלא נתמלאה המדה למוכר משנתמלאה המדה ללוקח.
Im ad shelo nismala hamida lamoicher, mishenismala hamida lalokeiach. If the container,
you know, the vessel that's being filled has not yet been filled
up, it's not full, then the wine or the oil still belongs
to the seller. Once it's full, now the buyer takes possession of
it. Why should that be the case? So what the גמרא Gemara
is going to say is this is in line with the ברייתא
Braita that we taught earlier and that understands that we're dealing with
a vessel that's owned neither by the buyer or the seller, but
by a third party. And the implicit understanding is that the buyer
owns it while he has not yet filled it up, and then
ownership or rights of usage transfer to, excuse me, the seller owns
it while it is not yet filled up, while he's still in
the process of filling it up, and then ownership slash rights of
usage transfer to the buyer once it's filled up. So then once
it's filled up, now it's the buyer's. Now he's קונה koneh with
a קנין של כלי. kinyan shel kli. Is it in the domain
of the owner or not, of the seller? That was a discussion
earlier. Okay, but that's the basic idea that whose כלי kli it
is changes once it's filled up. משנתמלאה המדה ללוקח. Mishenismala hamida lalokeiach.
ואם היה סרסור ביניהם, Ve'im haya sarsur beinehem, and if there was
a middleman between them, and we'll get to what exactly the role
of the middleman is. נשברה החבית נשברה לסרסור. Nishbera hachavis nishbera lasarsur.
If the barrel broke, then it's the סרסור's, sarsur סרסור's sarsur loss.
That is his loss.
So what does, you know, what does this mean exactly? So what's
the concept here? So רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot have an interesting
debate.
רשב"ם Rashbam says that basically this is basically making a statement that
anytime you use a middleman,
that he basically is taking possession. So imagine, right, this is the
question about is it consignment or is he, you know, buying it
wholesale, selling it retail. So you have the guy that, you have
all these farmers that have all their private parts of land, and
you have the guy that buys up all the apples from each
individual farmer and he collects them all, right? And then he goes
ahead and you know, and he sells them, you know, to each
store owner. All right? Or you know, you can imagine, that would
be like one scenario. Or he just sells them himself. He's the,
you know, he's the wholesaler and then he, you know, sells them,
buys wholesale, sells retail. Okay. So he's the middleman. But now in
that case, how is it, what's the implicit understanding? Is the implicit
understanding these remain my apples until you sell, and then you'll sell
my apples for me and I will give you a fee? That
is consignment. Or is it that you buy my apples from me,
you pay me the money, and then you go ahead and sell
it? So the רשב"ם Rashbam understands that it is the latter and
that's what the משנה Mishna is saying. If there is a middleman
that is buying up from individual, you know, from individual producers or
store owners and then selling to homeowners, so he is actually buying
it up. He is not selling it on consignment and any loss
therefore is his loss, and if the barrel breaks, it's his loss.
תוספות Tosafot says no, if that were true, why did it go
to a new case of that the barrel broke? It should have
said that the price went up or down. You know, there's huge
implications. Did you buy it? I mean, I also want to know
when is the money being paid? Also would be an extremely relevant
question. But if you bought it, you know, everything is,
it's all depends on whether you're selling it in consignment or whether
you bought it. So why did you specifically jump to this case
of breaking the barrel rather than a million other scenarios if you
wanting to back out or who knows, or the price went up
or down? So תוספות Tosafot says the opposite, that this standard case
here is one of consignment. If it's one of consignment then why
if the barrel broke does, is it his loss? Because תוספות Tosafot
is saying what it's saying is that if, that he, it would
be his negligence if the barrel broke, you know, and therefore he
has to pay because it's his negligence. It's really shifting completely the
framework and it's not about does he own it or not, he
doesn't own it, but he's responsible for making sure that it's a
good barrel and it doesn't break and if not then he is
liable. Okay, so one or the other, you really just wonder wouldn't
there be a lot of other indicators as to whether he was
buying it or doing it on consignment. Anyway, okay.
Now וחייב להטיף לו. Vechayav lehatif lo. Here's the part I was
thinking about. When it is being sold, you're selling somebody the wine
or oil, להטיף לו שלוש טיפין. Lehatif lo shalosh tipin.
Now, you have to add three extra drops. So what does this
mean?
It means, you know, if I go ahead and I measure out
a gallon of oil and now I'm pouring it into your vessel,
so it's going to take a long time for me to hold
that gallon measure upside down until all the oil
comes. What I have to do is just wait till three drops
after it basically all comes out, and then I'm holding it and
it's drip, drip, drip. Those like three drops after the stuff coming
from the sides of the wall, like that's enough. That's one way
of understanding. Another is, I filled up your vessel and I'm adding
three drops, just you know, like when you go and you buy
fruit from one of these guys who sell it on the street.
In at least my experience is, they measure it out in their
main thing and then they throw in a few extra grapes or
something just to make sure that you know you're getting your full
amount. All right, so anyway, two possible interpretations. We'll see more in
the גמרא. Gemara. הרכינה ומצץ Harchina u-mitzetz הרי של מוכר. harei shel
mocher.
Now,
if the seller, you know, incline the vessel and the stuff still
was stuck to the edges of the vessel, then the stuff that's
remaining on the sides of the inside walls, that belongs to the
seller. Even though if it was a full gallon measured out and
you're keeping the stuff that's on the sides of the wall, you're
not pouring out the full gallon, nevertheless it would take way too
much time to do it, and we just said that you are
allowed to keep that, that belongs to the seller. Okay. והחנוני V'hachanvani
אינו חייב להטיף eino chayav l'hatif שלש טיפין. shalosh tipin. Now that's
true if you're selling as a private homeowner. But if you are
a storekeeper, then you don't even have to do the three drops.
You just have so much traffic that you don't even have the
patience to do the—or we didn't demand from you the patience and
the time to do even the three drops. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehuda omer ערב שבת עם חשיכה erev shabbos im chashecha פטור. patur.
If it's ערב שבת Erev Shabbos right before, as it's right before
it's getting dark, then you're exempt. The גמרא Gemara is going to
discuss whether is he being—going on the idea of the חנוני chanvani
or the idea of the homeowner. So we'll see that in the
גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So first
גמרא Gemara wants to understand the case about why it matters whether
the vessel is filled or not. So the גמרא Gemara says: המידה
דמאן? Hamida d'man? This measuring vessel which it, you know, ownership shifts
once it's filled, who owns it? אילימא Ileima מידה דלוקח, mida d'lokeiach,
if it's owned by the buyer, עד שלא נתמלאה ad shelo nishtamlah
המידה hamida למוכר, l'mocher, why do we say that until it's been
filled the stuff still belongs to the seller? מידה דלוקח הוא. mida
d'lokeiach hu. It's the buyer's vessel and he should be buying every
bit that goes in. ואלא V'ela מידה דמוכר. mida d'mocher. All right,
so let's say it's the seller's vessel. So if that's true, משנתמלאה
mishe'nishtamlah המידה ללוקח, hamida l'lokeiach,
so the משנה Mishnah says once it's filled, now the buyer owns
it. Why is that true? מידה דמוכר הוא. mida d'mocher hu. It
belongs to him, it doesn't make any sense. If it's in the
same vessel then whoever's vessel it is should have the ownership. Why
does it matter if it's filled or not? So the גמרא Gemara
says: אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, says רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
במידת סרסור. B'midas sirsur. It is
the—it's the vessel of the go-between and he is letting the buyer
and the seller use it. And again, similar to the ברייתא Baraita
that we taught earlier, it is implicitly the seller has rights until
it's full and
then it belongs or has—the buyer has rights once it's filled. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: wait a minute, והא מדקתני סיפא, vadmi
ka-tani seifa, ואם היה סרסור ביניהם v'im haya sirsur beineihem נשברה החבית
נשברה לסרסור. nishbar ha-chavis nishbar l'sirsur. The next case is when there's
a go-between, and if there's a go-between and the barrel breaks, then
it's the go-between's loss. So the גמרא Gemara says: מכלל דרישא לאו
בסרסור עסקינן. miklal d'reisha lav b'sirsur askinan. So it's clear that the
first case of the משנה Mishnah we're not dealing with a go-between.
The גמרא Gemara says no: רישא Reisha מידה בלא סרסור, mida belo
sirsur, סיפא seifa בסרסור עצמו. b'sirsur atzmo. The first case the go-between
is only lending you his vessel. Okay, he's not actually playing any
role. And in that case it belongs to the seller until it's
full and then it belongs—or has rights to—the buyer has rights to
it once it's filled. If the person is actually playing a role,
this go-between,
then he assumes a degree of responsibility, either according to the רשב"ם
Rashbam he actually is understood to be the—to buy from the original
seller and then sell to the final buyer, or at least consignment
but he has responsibility for negligence and if the barrel breaks.
Okay. Next case of the משנה. Mishnah. הרכינה ומצץ Harchina u-mitzetz הרי
של מוכר. harei shel mocher. If he tips it, then stuff is
left out on the edges, it belongs to the seller.
כי סליק Hisalik רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, when רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, אשכחיה לזעירי. ashkachei l'Zeiri. He found
זעירי. Zeiri. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מי כאן תנא דאתנייה רב מידות?
mikun tana d'asniyei Rav midos?
Is there a תנא Tanna that רב Rav taught the מידות midos
to? Meaning these משניות mishnayot about measurements or ברייתות, Barayot, you know.
So now there's an interesting different גרסא girsa between רשב"ם Rashbam and
תוספות. Tosafot. Is there a תנא Tanna that רב Rav taught his
sort of, you know, Tannaitic teachings or whatever מימרות memras or whatever
about measurements, or Or is there the תנא tanna who taught רב
Rav these? But anyway, he wanted to know, get to some original
material here or get to the tradition around these teachings. So אחוי
achvey רב יצחק בר אבדימי. Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. He pointed out,
oh, רב יצחק בר אבדימי, Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, you have some
questions about measurements and pouring and the whole thing? Go to רב
יצחק בר אבדימי. Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. He either was רב'ס Rav's
teacher about this or רב'ס Rav's student. Okay. אמר ליה, amar lei,
מאי קא קשיא לך? mai ka kashya lach? So רב יצחק בר
אבדימי Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi said, what's bothering you? Clearly, there's some
problem that you're trying to resolve. דתנן, d'tnan, because we taught in
the משנה, mishna, הכינו מיצה הרי הוא של מוכר, hichino mitztah harei
hu shel mocher, that after you've tipped it, now stuff is still
adhering after the three drops to the edges of the inside walls,
the seller gets to keep that. So what's bothering you? What must
be bothering you is ותנן, v'tnan, that that seems to contradict another
משנה, mishna, הכינו מיצה הרי זו תרומה, hichino mitztah harei zu truma,
which says that if you are measuring out תרומה truma and you
measure out
a hundred units of oil, then those or
you measure out ninety-eight, תרומה'ס truma's supposed to be two percent, then
the last two units that you're measuring of all the new oil
that you have are going to be the תרומה truma of it
and you're pouring them into, let's say, the vessel of the כהן.
kohen. And it says the stuff that is left in your measuring
vessel is still תרומה. truma. So that seems to contradict. Here we're
saying
that when there's stuff left on the inside walls, it belongs to
the
original owner, to the seller. So if that's true in a transaction
case, then why isn't it also true in a תרומה truma case?
Why does that stuff that remains belong to the כהן? kohen? Why
shouldn't it belong to the homeowner? So אמר ליה, amar lei, איתמר
עלה, itmar ala, but it was said on this, there's a resolution.
אמר רב אבא, amar Rav Abba, משום יאוש בעלים נגעו בה. mishum
yeush ba'alim nangu bah. The reason here it's different is not because
of technically who should own it, but because of יאוש. yeush. You
measured out a full unit, a full gallon of that oil for
the buyer. The buyer should own even the stuff on the wall.
And when you take it as תרומה truma and you say it's
תרומה, truma, it's all תרומה, truma, even the stuff that's going to
stick on the wall. But when you're trying to give the buyer
his stuff and you've got that thin film left on the inside
wall, then even though it still belongs to the buyer,
he doesn't have the patience to wait around for you to drip,
drip, drip, drip, and therefore we just assume that he waives his
rights, he's מייאש, miya'esh, he lets you keep it. So technically, everything
in the vessel belongs to the buyer, but he foregoes the need
for you to give him the stuff on the wall. But when
it comes to תרומה, truma, if you declared it תרומה, truma, all
of it is תרומה truma and all of it is קודש. kodesh.
Okay, that makes a lot of sense. וחנווני אינו חייב להטיף. v'chanvani
eino chayav l'hatif. וחנווני v'chanvani doesn't have to, the store owner,
because he's got so much business. And then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says ערב שבת. erev shabbos. So איבעיא להו, iba'u l'hu, רבי יהודה
ארישא קאי ולקולא או דילמא אסיפא קאי ולחומרא? Rabbi Yehuda a-reisha ka'i
u-l'kulah o dilma a-seifa ka'i u-l'chumra? Is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda talking
about the first case and saying to the חכמים chachamim who say
you have to do the three drops, I, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
say that ערב שבת erev shabbos you don't have to do the
three drops? So he's being go easy on normal homeowners. That's one
way to read it. או דילמא אסיפא קאי ולחומרא, o dilma a-seifa
ka'i u-l'chumra, maybe he's going on the second case. You the חכמים
chachamim say store owners never have to do the three drops. I
say only on ערב שבת erev shabbos they don't have to. I'm
going to be stricter and limit that allowance to only ערב שבת.
erev shabbos. תא שמע דתניא, ta shema d'tanya, רבי יהודה אומר ערב
שבת עם חשיכה חנווני פטור מפני שחנווני טרוד. Rabbi Yehuda omer erev
shabbos im chashecha chanvani patur mipnei she-chanvani tarud. That רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says on Friday afternoon, as it's getting dark, the store owner
is that's when the store owner is exempt from the three dots
because he is so under so much pressure. But other times, I
disagree with you the חכמים chachamim and I say a normal store
owner is still obligated in those three drops. Okay, that was that
משנה. mishna. Let's now look at the next one. השולח את בנו
אצל חנווני. hasholeach es bno etzel chanvani. Somebody sends his son to
the store owner, his underage son, to go pick up, as we're
going to see,
an איסר, issar, excuse me, worth of oil. Now some have the
גרסא ופונדיון בידו. girsa u-pundyon b'yado. He sent him to the store
owner with a פונדיון, pundyon, which is worth two איסר. issar. Let's
call it a twenty dollar bill and he wants to buy ten
dollars' worth of oil. So we're going to read it that way.
ומדד לו באיסר שמן. u-madda lo b'issar shemen. And the store owner
now measured out for the son ten dollars' worth of oil, which
is what the son was told to buy. ונתן לו את האיסר.
v'nasan lo es ha-issar. And he gave him back, so here's the
oil, and here's by the way another your ten dollars change. שיבר
את הצלוחית. shiber es hatzluchis.
Now the son... is bringing it back and on his way back
he broke the jug, the oil spilled, he lost the ten dollars.
Who's liable? חנוני חייב. Chenvani chayav. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
the store owner is liable. Why?
Because the son is not בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. He can't do
a קנין. Kinyan. He can't take legal possession of it. He can't
go ahead and be trusted to guard it. So the חנוני Chenvani
is giving when the חנוני Chenvani gives him oil and gives him
a ten dollar bill, okay, that's still the חנוני's Chenvani oil and
the חנוני's Chenvani ten dollar bill.
And if the oil spills before the guy gets home, then the
guy before the kid gets home, then the father can say you
have my twenty dollars
and I don't have anything from you. I don't have oil, I
don't have ten dollars change. So the חנוני Chenvani says I understand
I gave it to your kid. Says my kid? It's not me
yet. He didn't take possession from me, but you still took my
twenty dollars. Okay and that's the position that the חנוני Chenvani is
חייב. chayav. The חנוני Chenvani still has to make good. He took
the twenty dollars and nothing has transferred yet to the owner.
רבי יהודה פוטר, Rabbi Yehuda poter, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda exempts
שעל מנת כן שלחו. She'al menas ken shalacho. For that reason he
sent the kid. Implicitly in sending the kid, right? If that were
the הלכה, Halacha, I'm imagining רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying, then no
store owner is ever going to sell anything to a kid. Okay
and you also don't want the store owner to just take your
twenty bucks and say fine, when your father comes around I'll give
him the oil and I'll give him the change. Really? Is that
what he is that what the father wants? No. He wants his
kid to bring him back the oil and the change, oil change.
Anyway, so therefore רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even though technically you're
right the kid can't do a קנין Kinyan and so on, it's
implicit that the father is saying you give it to the kid
and I will assume that that's what I'm buying and the change
and that will be you'll be off the hook and you can
keep my twenty dollars as long as you do that. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. ומודים חכמים לרבי יהודה בזמן שהצלוחית ביד
התינוק, Umodim chachamim le'Rabbi Yehuda bizman shehatzlochis beyad hatinok,
but the sages do agree to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that if
the child, the infant, not an infant, the child is still holding
on to the jug ומדד חנוני לתוכה שחנוני פטור, Umadad chenvani lesochah
shechenvani patur,
and the חנוני Chenvani measures into it, that in that case the
חנוני Chenvani is exempt and you know for some reason that case
he is off the hook. Now that's very unclear why that should
be true, okay, and the רשב"ם Rashbam immediately points out we're only
talking about the jug, not the oil because according to the חכמים
Chachamim at the end of the day the oil, the ten bucks,
it still belongs to the חנוני, Chenvani, but the jug, assuming that
this jug, because who mentioned the jug? Right? I
mean it said that he gave him the oil and the ten
dollars change. So the simple read of the משנה Mishnah is that
the jug belongs to the father and he sent the kid with
the jug, like nowadays everybody you have to have your own shopping
bags, okay, he sent the kid with the jug and the חנוני
Chenvani gave him the oil, gave him the ten dollars.
And in this case, okay if that's true, then why should the
חנוני Chenvani ever be liable for the jug? So the משנה Mishnah
is distinguishing between did the חנוני Chenvani take the jug or leave
it in the kid's hands? If he left it in the kid's
hands, he's not liable. Why should he be? It was never his.
Okay, but if he took it, then he assumes a degree of
liability and we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. All right, so
let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא באיסר ושמן, Bishlama be'isar veshemen, I get the idea,
the debate around the ten dollar change and the oil. בהא פליגי,
Beha peligi, this is the debate. דרבנן סברי להודיע שדריה, Derabbanan savri
lehodiya shadrei, the rabbis hold that I sent my kid to inform
you that I wanted to buy the oil, but I never said
that you have a right to send it back and that you'll
be off the hook if you send it back with my kid.
Again, it's a little crazy. Why am I sending my kid if
I'm still going to have to go and pick it up myself?
I don't know. Maybe I want my wife to come pick it
up and you know but my wife doesn't have the money so
I'm sending the ten dollars. Anyway, it's hard to believe especially if
the kid is carrying the jug. Okay, but basically what I understand
is that even though it's true that obviously this is the way
I'm going to read it, the father does want the oil and
the change back from the kid, he never explicitly told the store
owner that he was waiving the store owner's liability or that he
would the store owner was like seen to have given him his
money's worth as soon as he handed it to the kid. And
therefore halachically the objective הלכה Halacha still is that the father doesn't
own it, the kid doesn't own it, it's still the חנוני's Chenvani
and therefore if it gets lost that's on the חנוני. Chenvani. If
it breaks or gets lost. That's what the rabbis hold. רבי יהודה
סבר לשדורי לשדריה. Rabbi Yehuda savar leshadorei leshadrei. No, I sent the
kid in order for the חנוני Chenvani for the store owner to
send me back my oil and my change. In that case, even
though the kid doesn't technically own it, it's implicit that I'm saying
to him take the twenty dollars, give the change and the oil
to my kid and then you will be off the hook. You
will have done what I've asked. Okay, that's the debate, fine. But
now, let's try to understand what's going on with this jug, okay?
But, but אלא השבת צלוחית אבדה מדעתו? Ela hashvat sheluchit avda midato?
But in terms of the jug, why is the storekeeper liable? That
was a willing destruction or loss. What does that mean? It means
when the father gave the jug to the kid,
then he was putting it in the hands of somebody that was
not halachically able to be responsible, whether the kid was responsible or
not. And therefore, you know, the
חנווני—it's chanvani already if something happens to the jug, the father has
already been sort of almost like willingly put it in a situation
where it could get destroyed and nobody would be sort of liable
for that. So how is the חנווני chanvani liable for taking it
from the kid and giving it back to the kid? Although the
father already gave it to the kid and was okay with whatever
was going to happen with it. Where does the חנווני's chanvani liability
come in here? Now, you might be asking how is that different
than the twenty bucks? Okay, because the twenty bucks also the father
gave the kid and the kid could have lost. So the point
is just giving the twenty bucks or the jug to the kid
does not mean that anybody can come and steal the twenty bucks
or steal the jug from the kid. It still belongs to the
father. So when the חנווני chanvani took the twenty bucks, even though
if something would have happened it would have been the father's fault,
and he's now pocketed it, he's taken possession of it, he now
has the father's twenty dollars and now he owes the father twenty
dollars worth of produce or of change. Okay, but as far as
the jug is concerned, he didn't pocket the jug. He took it,
he filled it, he gave it back, where does his liability kick
in? Even if he gave it back to the kid, it started
with the kid. All right, so that's an excellent question. So אלא
השבת צלוחית אבדה מדעתו. Ela hashvat sheluchit avda midato. אמר רב הושעיה
הכא בבעל הבית מוכר צלוחיות עסקינן. Amar Rav Oshaya hacha beba'al habayit
mocher sheluchot askinan.
We are talking about a case where the homeowner, meaning me who
is sending my kid, I actually sell jugs. Okay, this is a
very weak אוקימתא. okimta. I know my kid is going to the
store owner and the store owner might want to buy my jugs.
So I'm sending him this jug which he's going to fill up
with oil for my kid to take back to me, but also
it's an opportunity for him to look at it and decide if
he wants to maybe purchase my jugs. All right, וכגון שנטלו חנווני
על מנת לבקרו. Ukegon shenatalo chanvani al menat levakro.
And the storekeeper when he took it, took it, the understanding was
like it's a whole other narrative going on here. All right, not
only am I sending my kid to get oil, but we've been
talking, you know, offline about maybe you buying my jugs and I'm
sending you the jug along so you can take a look at
it when my kid brings it for the oil. And then you,
the store owner, you take a look at it and you inspect
it. And therefore what? וכדשמואל. Uchdishmuel. And now it's שמואל's Shmuel teaching.
דאמר שמואל הנוטל כלי מן האומן על מנת לבקרו. De'amar Shmuel hanotel
kli min ha'uman al menat levakro. If somebody takes a vessel from
a craftsman in order to test it, in order to decide if
he wants to buy it, על מנת לבקרו ונאנס בידו, al menat
levakro vene'enas beyado, and then even some complete accident happens, no negligence
at all while you are looking at it, you know, you're going
into a store and you're picking up the merchandise and you're inspecting
it, and then some freak accident occurs and it breaks,
חייב, chayav, you're liable. All right, now, why are you liable? So
there's a whole long תוספות Tosafot and a רשב"ם. Rashbam. There are
two different explanations. One which is the easiest, although it's questionable if
it sort of explains everything as we're going to continue, but conceptually
it's the easiest here, is that you're considered like a שואל, shoel,
a borrower. I'm taking your thing, I'm looking at it, okay, right
now in this—now you might in the end get a deal out
of it. But right now in this exchange, you are not getting
anything right now because I can return it to you and I'm
just having it under my control in order to inspect it. So
I'm the only one getting anything out of this immediate transaction, so
I am a שואל shoel and therefore if something happens, I am
liable.
And to explain that here would mean the חנווני chanvani gets my
jug, he's looking at it and deciding whether he wants to buy
it, he's a שואל, shoel, then he gives it back to the
kid and it breaks and therefore I am liable because something happened
to it, I assumed liability or maybe, you know, just giving it
back to the kid was being irresponsible. If once I'm a שואל
shoel I have to give it back to the original owner, that's
a whole question exactly we won't get into right now. However, if
it never left the hands of the kids, then I'm off the
hook. Okay, that's one way. The other way goes even further than
saying the person inspecting it is a שואל, shoel, it's... It's like
he bought it. He buys it, but he has a right to
give it back, but as long as he's inspecting it he's considered
to be the quasi-owner.
All right and then that would according to that obviously then I'm
liable if something breaks before the original owner gets it back. All
right. So that's that would be the explanation. But it's a really
weak אוקימתא ukimta that the person is also trying to sell the
store owner his jug. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
about this. לימא דשמואל תנאי היא, Leima d'Shmuel tanna'i hi, okay? So
then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda maybe are we claiming now that שמואל
Shmuel is a debate of תנאים Tanna'im because you know now because
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda seems to therefore you know be disagreeing with
it. The way you know because the way we explained רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda before was only about what was being purchased, the oil
or the ten dollars of change that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
that was implicit. Take the twenty dollars, give it to my kid,
you'll be off the hook. But as far as the the jug
is concerned, you know, he took the jug to inspect it. According
to the חכמים Chachamim he becomes a שואל, sho'el, he becomes liable.
So are we going to say that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda even when he takes the jug to inspect it he doesn't
become liable? So that would make the שמואל Shmuel's position a debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים. Chachamim. And we would
rather for שמואל Shmuel you know not say that. שמואל Shmuel would
rather his position not be you know debated by the תנאים Tanna'im
but be that that there be that everybody would agree with it.
Okay. So is that what we're really saying? אי הכי אימא סיפא—excuse
I hachi eima seifa my line—לימא דשמואל תנאי היא, Leima d'Shmuel tanna'i
hi, אלא ela so
okay rather than saying that and again what a what a weak
אוקימתא ukimta to say that it was the store owner was also
trying to sell his jug. So we're not going to go there
and then that would make the Rabbis and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
debate שמואל Shmuel's position. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו Rabba v'Rav Yosef
d'amri tarvayhu here's how we're going to explain what's going on with
the jug. הכא בחנוני מוכר צלוחיות עסקינן. Hacha b'chanvani mocher tzluchi'ot askinan.
It's the opposite. It's that the חנוני chanvani is selling jugs. Okay.
And therefore part of what the kid is buying from the store
with the twenty dollars is also the jug, like when they ask
you in the store, do you also want to buy a paper
bag to go with it? Okay. So that makes at least a
little more sense. ואזדא רבי יהודה לטעמיה ורבנן לטעמייהו. V'azda Rabbi Yehuda
l'taamei v'Rabbanan l'taameihu. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda's going to his way
and the Rabbis their reasoning. It's exactly what we said before.
According to the Rabbis the store owner owes everything until it gets
to the hand of the father, so the jug, the oil, the
ten dollars all still belongs to the store owner. And according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda all of that was what I wanted you
to give my kid so you're off the hook. And it's no
different than any of the other things being discussed. So the גמרא
Gemara says no that can't be because then what do you do
with the end of the משנה? Mishna? אי הכי אימא סיפא: I
hachi eima seifa: מודים חכמים לרבי יהודה בזמן שהצלוחית ביד התינוק ומדדה
החנוני לתוכה החנוני פטור, modim Chachamim le-Rabbi Yehuda bizman she-tzluchit b'yad hatinok,
u-medadah ha-chanvani l'tocha, ha-chanvani patur, that the חכמים Chachamim agree that if
you know the kid is holding on to the jug then the
חנוני chanvani is off the hook. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
אמרת לאו דאורי שדריה. v'ha amarta lo duy shadri.
But you said that he only sent him to inform, meaning what?
Meaning that like even if the kid is holding the jug, now
of course it's a little bizarre, if the חנוני chanvani is selling
the jugs, what's the scenario? I mean that's really what the גמרא
Gemara should have asked. Who cares if the kid is holding it
or the חנוני chanvani is holding it? In the end of the
day it started in the possession of the חנוני, chanvani, he's holding
the jug and eventually the kid is going to own it, right?
But what the גמרא Gemara is—so that's sort of what the גמרא
Gemara is asking. It's just asking it from a different direction. It's
saying look whatever the difference is between the חנוני chanvani holding the
jug when it's being filled or the kid holding the jug, if
according to the חכמים Chachamim the point is that that you remain
totally on the hook with the items you're selling until they get
back to the father and the fact that I'm sending you my
son is only to inform you I want to buy it but
but there's no waiver of liability, then whoever was holding the jug
it doesn't matter, that jug was something yours and I'm not liable
for it until until it gets into my possession. Okay another way
of saying that would just be then who cares if the kid
is holding the jug? It's the חנוני chanvani's jug just like it
was the oil and the ten dollars change of the חנוני. chanvani.
All right. So so we are going to try to find a
better explanation tomorrow for this. Clearly it seems the simplest explanation is
without a doubt that the jug was sent by the father. That's
why it wasn't mentioned that the חנוני chanvani gave the jug, okay?
And what we have to figure—and then that's why if the kid
is still holding onto the jug the חנוני chanvani has no liability.
And what we have to figure out is where does the חנוני
chanvani's liability come when the חנוני chanvani takes the jug out of
the kid's hands? We tried to say that he was inspecting it
whether to buy it, שמואל, Shmuel, that didn't work. So tomorrow we
will see if we can find a better explanation of where that
liability comes from when he takes it out of the kid's hands.